Arthur Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Arthur Family Papers 1817-1972 (bulk 1874-1972)
MSS49577
Arthur family
20,000 items 75 containers plus 2 oversize 31 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, diaries, scrapbooks, writings, printed matter, clippings, and miscellaneous material chiefly of Chester Alan Arthur II (1864-1937), sportsman and rancher, and Chester Alan ("Gavin") Arthur III (1901-1972), author and bohemian, son and grandson respectively of President Chester Alan Arthur (1829-1886).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Agar, Herbert, 1897-1980--Correspondence.; Andrews family.; Andrews, Loring.; Arthur family.; Arthur, Chester Alan, 1829-1886--Family.; Arthur, Chester Alan, 1864-1937. Chester Alan Arthur papers. 1874-1937.; Arthur, Chester Alan, 1901-1972. Chester Alan Arthur papers. 1853-1972.; Arthur, Myra Fithian Andrews, 1870-1935.; Arthur, William A., b. ca. 1833.; Fithian family.; Haynesworth, Malvina Ann Arthur, 1832-1916.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968--Correspondence.; Watts, Alan, 1915-1973--Correspondence.
Organizations
Utopian Society of America.
Subjects
American periodicals.; Astrology.; Bohemianism.; Clubs.; Cooking.; Horses.; Hunting.; Occultism.; Poetry.; Ranches--Colorado--Costilla County.; Republicanism--Ireland--History--20th century.; Sexology--Research.
Places
Europe--Description and travel.; Ireland--Politics and government--20th century.; Trinchera Ranch (Colo.); United States--Description and travel.
Titles
Dune Forum.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of the Arthur family, consisting primarily of those of Chester Alan Arthur II (1864-1937) and Chester Alan Arthur III (1901-1972), were given to the Library of Congress by Thomas C. Reeves in 1973.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Arthur Family Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Arthur Family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Chester Alan Arthur II
Date Event
1864, July 25 Born, New York, N.Y.
1885 Graduated, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J.
1887 Sailed for Europe
1900 Married Myra Fithian Andrews (divorced 1927) Moved to Colorado Springs, Colo.
1901 Birth of Chester Alan Arthur (1901-1972)
1934 Married Rowena Dashwood Graves
1937, July 18 Died, Colorado Springs, Colo.
Chester Alan Arthur III
Date Event
1901, Mar. 21 Born, Colorado Springs, Colo.
1920-1922 Attended Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1922 Married Charlotte Wilson (divorced 1932) Served as Secretary to Irish Republican delegation in Lausanne, Switzerland
1922-1924 Lived in Ireland
1931 Moved to Oceano, Calif.
1931-1934 Founded commune near Pismo Beach, Calif.
1933-1934 Founded Dune Forum and published six issues
1934 Joined Utopian Society
1935 Married Esther Murphy Strachey (divorced 1961)
1940-1941 Secretary, Democratic State Central Committee of California
1949-1951 Taught at San Quentin prison, Calif.
1952 Graduated, San Francisco State College, San Francisco, Calif.
1962 Published The Circle of Sex. San Francisco: Pangraphic Press
1965 Married Ellen Janson
1966 Published enlarged edition of The Circle of Sex. New Hyde Park, N.Y.: University Books
1972, Apr. 28 Died, San Francisco, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Arthur family span the years 1817 to 1972, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1874-1972. Although the collection consists largely of the papers of Chester Alan Arthur II (1864-1937) and Chester Alan Arthur III (1901-1972), it includes papers of President Chester Alan Arthur's sister, Malvina Ann Arthur Haynesworth; his brother, William A. Arthur, Jr.; Chester Alan Arthur II's first wife, Myra Fithian Andrews; his sister, Ellen Arthur Pinkerton; Chester Alan Arthur III's first wife, Charlotte Wilson Arthur, and his second wife, Esther Murphy Strachey Arthur. Other members of the Arthur Andrews, and Fifthian families are also represented in the collection. The papers are organized in ten series: Chester Alan Arthur II Papers, Myra Fithian Andrews Arthur Papers, Ellen Arthur Pinkerton Papers, Chester Alan Arthur III Papers, Malvina Ann Arthur Haynesworth Papers, William A. Arthur, Jr., Papers, Andrews Family Papers, Fithian Family Papers, Miscellany, and Oversize.
After the death of Chester Alan Arthur (1829-1886), Chester Alan Arthur II withdrew from Columbia University School of Law and sailed for Europe where he remained for over a decade. His papers for this period reveal his interest in women, horses, and cuisine. His correspondence abounds with letters from female admirers, and his diaries, scrapbooks, and general correspondence disclose his frequent participation in driving horse-drawn coaches through the French countryside. In 1897, Alan ("A-lan," pronounced as in "plan"), as he liked to be called, unsuccessfully sought appointment as United States ambassador to the Netherlands. His marriage in 1900 to Myra Fithian Andrews raised his family's hopes that he would now choose a vocation or a profession, but he preferred to live on income from investments. He belonged to clubs in England, France, New York, California, and Colorado and mingled with the social elite of two continents. He maintained a home in Colorado Springs, Colorado, where for several years he was the major stockholder in a company owning the Trinchera Estate, a 250,000 acre ranch. The company cut timber, raised cattle, mined for gold, and established a game park reserve for the preservation of bison, elk, antelope, and other rare game animals.
Chester Alan Arthur III was more interested in social and political causes than in elegant living. During the 1920s, as his correspondence documents, he joined the Irish Republican Movement. For four years, in Ireland, Paris, and New York, he contributed his services. During the years 1931-1934, under the adopted ancestral name of Gavin Arthur, he organized in the dunes near Pismo Beach, California, a commune devoted to art and literature. He founded a magazine entitled Dune Forum, designed to establish communication between the intellectuals and the masses; six issues of Dune Forum were published.
In 1934, he joined the Utopian Society of America, and for several years thereafter he worked in its behalf. His correspondence for this period includes letters from Upton Sinclair and Herbert Agar. In the late 1930's Arthur became interested in party politics. In 1940, he accepted the post of secretary of the Democratic State Central Committee of California, but in 1941, convinced that the party had betrayed his principles, he resigned.
According to autobiographical manuscripts in the papers, he served in the United States Army and the merchant marine during World War II. After the war, he lived in New York City, where he sold books, tutored, and drew unemployment compensation. In 1949 he went to California and for a time found employment as a teacher-counselor in the state prison at San Quentin. During the 1950s he sustained himself by selling newspapers on the streets of San Francisco. Feeling handicapped by his lack of a formal education, he earned a bachelor's degree at San Francisco State College. Ultimately he became a freelance writer, a professional astrologer, and a student of the occult and of sexology.
Throughout his life, Arthur cultivated a wide variety of people, including political leaders, writers, entertainers, sexologists, and social misfits and outcasts. He was married successively to Charlotte Wilson, a dancer who was also a writer; Esther Murphy Strachey, an expatriate intellectual, the sister of Gerald Murphy, who had formerly been married to John Strachey, a leader of the British Labor Party; and, in his last years, to Ellen Janson, a longtime friend who had helped him launch Dune Forum. He wrote poetry and fiction for which he apparently found no market and began philosophical and historical works that he never completed. In 1962, he published The Circle of Sex, a study of male and female sexuality; in 1966, he published a revised and enlarged edition. Portions of the manuscript of the book and four containers of other writings are in his papers.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in ten series:
Chester Alan Arthur II Papers, 1874-1937
Myra Fithian Andrews Arthur Papers, 1882-1935
Ellen Arthur Pinkerton Papers, 1879-1914
Chester Alan Arthur III Papers, 1853-1972
Malvina Ann Arthur Haynesworth Papers, 1853-1869
William A. Arthur, Jr., Papers, 1853-1914
Andrews Family Papers, 1903-1957
Fithian Family Papers, 1882-1960
Miscellany, 1817-1967
Oversize, 1817-1971
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm76049577
Container List
- Chester Alan Arthur II Papers, 1874-1937 (Box 1-17)
  - Diaries, 1887-1913 (Box 1-2)
    Arranged chronologically.
    - 1887-1890, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1891-1913, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Family Correspondence, 1877-1937 (Box 3-5)
    Arranged chronologically by month.
    - 1877-Sept. 1897, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - Oct. 1897-Oct. 1907, (7 folders) (Box 4)
    - Nov. 1907-Dec. 1911 (Box 5)
    - 1912-1937, undated, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1874-1935 (Box 6-11)
    - 1874-Dec. 1893, (6 folders) (Box 6)
    - Jan. 1894-Feb. 1898, (4 folders) (Box 7)
    - Mar. 1898-1907, (6 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1908-1914, (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - Jan. 1915-1935, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - Undated, (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Financial Papers, 1882-1937 (Box 12-13)
    Arranged chronologically by year.
    - 1882-1905, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1906-1937, undated, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Miscellany (Box 14-17)
    Arranged by type of material.
    - Address books (Box 14)
    - Calling cards (Box 14)
    - Fragments, (2 folders); (1 folders) (Box 14, Box 15)
    - Invitations, (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Legal papers (Box 16)
    - Lists (Box 16)
    - Menus (Box 16)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 16)
    - Notebooks (Box 16)
    - Political material (Box 17)
    - Programs (Box 17)
    - Related correspondence (Box 17)
    - Travels and itineraries (Box 17)
    - Writings (Box 17)
- Myra Fithian Andrews Arthur Papers, 1882-1935 (Box 18-29)
  - Diaries, 1902-1935 (Box 18-20)
    - 1902-1916, (5 folders) (Box 18)
    - 1917-1927, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - 1928-1935, (4 folders) (Box 20)
  - Family Correspondence, 1891-1935 (Box 21-26)
    - 1891-June 1911, (5 folders) (Box 21)
    - July 1911-1919, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1920-June 1923, (4 folders) (Box 23)
    - July 1923-June 1928, (4 folders) (Box 24)
    - July 1928-1931, (4 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1932-1935, undated, (4 folders) (Box 26)
  - General Correspondence, 1882-1935 (Box 27-29)
    - Apr. 1882-1919, (5 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1920-1930, (6 folders) (Box 28)
    - 1931-1935, undated, (3 folders) (Box 29)
  - Miscellany (Box 29)
    Address books.
    - Address books (Box 29)
- Ellen Arthur Pinkerton Papers, 1879-1914 (Box 30)
  Family correspondence.
  - Family correspondence. (Box 30)
- Chester Alan Arthur III Papers, 1853-1972 (Box 31-67)
  - Diaries, 1900-1966 (Box 31-32)
    Arranged chronologically by decade.
    - 1900-1929, (3 folders) (Box 31)
    - 1930-1966, (3 folders) (Box 32)
  - Family Correspondence, 1904-1971 (Box 33-35)
    - Nov. 1904-1925, (5 folders) (Box 33)
    - 1926-1937, (5 folders) (Box 34)
    - 1938-1971, undated, (5 folders) (Box 35)
  - General Correspondence, 1909-1972 (Box 36-50)
    - June 1909-1922, (5 folders) (Box 36)
    - 1923-Sept. 1926, (4 folders) (Box 37)
    - Oct. 1926-1929, (4 folders) (Box 38)
    - 1930-Dec. 1933, (4 folders) (Box 39)
    - Jan. 1934-1935, (4 folders) (Box 40)
    - 1936-1937, (4 folders) (Box 41)
    - Jan.-June 1939, (4 folders) (Box 42)
    - July 1939-1942, (5 folders) (Box 43)
    - Jan. 1943-1946, (4 folders) (Box 44)
    - 1947-1959, (4 folders) (Box 45)
    - 1960-1963, (5 folders) (Box 46)
    - 1964-1966, (3 folders) (Box 47)
    - 1967-1969, (3 folders) (Box 48)
    - 1970-1972, undated, (4 folders) (Box 49)
    - Undated, (4 folder) (Box 50)
  - Politics, 1936-1942 (Box 51)
    Primarily correspondence.
    - 1936-1942, undated (2 folders) (Box 51)
  - Charlotte Wilson Arthur, 1921-1966 (Box 51)
    Correspondence and writings.
    Correspondence arranged chronologically by month.
    - Correspondence, 1920-1966, undated, (3 folders) (Box 51)
    - Writings (Box 51)
  - Esther Murphy Arthur, 1924-1961 (Box 52)
    Correspondence and cancelled checks.
    Correspondence arranged chronologically by month
    - Correspondence, 1929-1961, undated, (4 folders) (Box 52)
    - Canceled checks, 1924-1929 (Box 52)
  - Edith L. DeSavary, 1924-1962 (Box 53)
    Correspondence.
    - Correspondence, 1946-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 53)
  - Writings, 1916-1972 (Box 53-57)
    Arranged chronologically with major titles alphabetically at end.
    - Chronological file (Box 53)
      - 1916-1930s, (3 folders) (Box 53)
      - 1940s-1970s, (5 folders) (Box 54)
      - Undated, (3 folders) (Box 55)
    - Alphabetical file (Box 55)
      - "Aspirations at Thirty" (Box 55)
      - Astrology (Box 55)
      - The Circle of Sex (Box 56)
      - "Full Circle", (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 56, Box 57)
      - "Notes on Freedom" (Box 57)
      - Poetry (Box 57)
      - "Priscilla", (2 folders) (Box 57)
      - Fragments (Box 57)
  - Miscellany, 1853-1972 (Box 58-67)
    - Address books, (3 folders) (Box 58)
    - Astrology (Box 58)
    - Books, The Voice of the Silence and the New Testament (Box 58)
    - Calling cards (Box 59)
    - Correspondence (copies), President Chester A. Arthur, (2 folders) (Box 59)
    - Correspondence related to Chester Alan Arthur III (Box 59)
      - 1922-1970 (Box 59)
      - Undated (Box 59)
    - Drawings (Box 59)
    - Financial papers, 1930-1971 (Box 60)
    - Fragments (Box 60)
      - 1912-1972, (3 folders) (Box 60)
      - Undated, (5 folders) (Box 61)
    - Greeting cards, (3 folders) (Box 62)
    - Invitations and announcements (Box 62)
    - Legal papers (Box 63)
    - List of dates copied from notebook courses (Box 63)
    - Memorabilia, Ireland, 1920s (Box 63)
    - Newspaper clippings, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 63, Box 64)
    - Notes relating to "Full Circle" (Box 64)
    - Pamphlets, The Circle of Sex (Box 64)
    - "People I Have Known" (Box 64)
    - Programs, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 64, Box 65)
    - Reeves, Thomas C., manuscript copies of articles (Box 66)
    - San Quentin prison, San Quentin, Calif. (Box 66)
    - Typescript of Ellen Herndon Arthur correspondence, 1877-1879 (Box 66)
    - Writings by others, (4 folders) (Box 66)
    - Copies of family letters and notes, 1853-1933, (2 folders) (Box 67)
    - How a British Subject Became President of the United States (1884), by A. P. Hinman (heavily annotated) (Box 67)
- Malvina Ann Arthur Haynesworth Papers, 1853-1869 (Box 68)
  Diaries.
  - Diaries, originals and typescripts (Box 68)
    - 1853 (Box 68)
    - 1869 (2 copies) (Box 68)
- William A. Arthur, Jr., Papers, 1853-1914 (Box 68-69)
  Diaries, correspondence, military papers, and miscellany.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Diaries, 1858-1881, (4 folders) (Box 68)
  - Correspondence (Box 69)
    - 1853-1914 (2 folders) (Box 69)
    - Copies (1843-1917) (Box 69)
  - Military papers, 1862-1891, (2 folders) (Box 69)
  - Miscellany, (2 folders) (Box 69)
- Andrews Family Papers, 1903-1957 (Box 69)
  Correspondence and miscellany, including writings of Loring Andrews.
  Correspondence arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence (Box 69)
  - Miscellany (Box 69)
- Fithian Family Papers, 1882-1960 (Box 70)
  Arranged chronologically
  - Correspondence, 1882-1960, undated, (3 folders) (Box 70)
- Miscellany, 1817-1967 (Box 71-75)
  Printed matter and scrapbooks.
  - Printed matter (Box 71)
    - Books, (4 folders) (Box 71)
    - Books and journals, (2 folders) (Box 72)
    - Books (Box 73)
    - Postcards, clippings, and related items removed from notebook covers (Box 73)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 74)
    - Chester Alan Arthur II (Box 74)
      - 1876-1883, undated (Box 74)
      - 1886-1957 (Box 74)
    - Andrews, Loring, 1930 (Box 75)
    - Arthur, Alan Arthur, III (Box 75)
      - 1897-1916, coaching clippings (Box 75)
      - 1956 (Box 75)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 75)
    - Connolly, R. B., 1856 (Box 75)
- Oversize, 1817-1971 (Box OV 1-OV 2)
  Account book, guest book, literary notes, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous oversize material relating mainly to Chester Alan Arthur, II.
  Arranged by type of material
  - Account book, 1817-1846, with literary notes by Chester Alan Arthur III, 1965-1967 (Box OV 1)
  - Guestbook, Myra Arthur, 1910-1969 (Box OV 1)
  - Scrapbooks, Chester Alan Arthur III (Box OV 2)
    - 1960-1971, undated (Box OV 2)
    - Undated (Box OV 2)